Eric W. Barker Papers
Eric Wilson Barker Papers
1930-1968
Barker, Eric Wilson.
0.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American poet (1905-1973). Correspondence, manuscripts, and published material.
148831
Biographical History
Eric Barker (1905-1973) was an American poet. Born and educated in England, he came to the United States at the age of 16 with his parents. Barker worked for short periods as a truck dispatcher, a gardener, a signal tower operator in a railroad yard, and a caretaker. His real "work" however was writing poetry and roaming the wild area around his home in Carmel, California. Among his books of poetry are The Planetary Heart (1942), Directions in the Sun (1956), A Ring in the Willows (1961), and Looking for Water (1964). He was awarded the Shelley Memorial Award of the Poetry Society of America in 1963.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Eric Barker Papers include one subject file, correspondence, manuscripts, and published material.
The single Subject file contains a photograph of the poet. Correspondence, all incoming, consists mainly of letters written between 1932 and 1959 from John Cowper Powys. There are also seven letters from Llewelyn Powys, most of which are to Barker's wife, dancer Madelynne Greene, and two letters from Robinson Jeffers. Manuscripts include a signed holograph poem and the galley proof of Barker's book, Looking for Water. Published material consists of a tearsheet from Spectrum (1968) to which Barker contributed two poems to the issue for which he was guest editor; an article by Evelyn Ames which appeared in the Literary Review; and clippings about Barker.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Poetry; Barker, Eric Wilson.; Greene, Madelynne.; Jeffers, Robinson, 1887-1962.; Powys, John Cowper, 1872-1963.; Poets, American -- 20th century.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 1965.
Inventory
- Subject file
  - Photograph of Eric Barker, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming correspondence
    - Gregory, Alyse, 1938; 1 item (Box 1)
    - Grey, Marian Powys, undated; 1 item (Box 1)
    - Jeffers, Robinson, 1955-1956; 2 items (Box 1)
    - Playter, Phyllis, 1941; 1 item (Box 1)
    - Powys, John Cowper, 1932-1959; undated; 151 items; 7 folders (Box 1)
    - Powys, Llewelyn, 1930; 1936,; undated; 7 items (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - "A Jade Pebble", signed holograph poem (Box 1)
  - Looking for Water, undated; galley proof (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Writings by
    - Poems from Spectrum, 1968; "For a Metal Sculpture Made Entirely From Spare Parts of Abandoned Cars" and "In Memory of John Cowper Powys"; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Writings about
    - Article - "Eric Barker - Figure in a Landscape" by Evelyn Ames, The Literary Review, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Clippings from Newsweek and various newspapers, 1961-1963 (Box 1)